Finding Aid for Robert Gesell Papers, 1921-1956
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Robert Gesell papers 1921-1956
Gesell, Robert, 1886-1954.
3 linear ft.
851307 Aa 2
Neurophysiologist; chairman of the physiology department of University of Michigan Medical School. Correspondence, medical school faculty minutes, annual reports of the department, lectures, speeches, and material on the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection, 1930; also photograph.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were transferred from the University of Michigan Medical School (donor no. 647 ) in 1956.
The collection is open to research.
Robert Gesell was born in Alma, Wisconsin in June 23, 1886. He graduated from the University of Wisconsin with a AB degree in 1910, and from Washington University in 1914 with his M.D. At Washington University, in addition to his tudies, he held various positions in his field of physiology (1910-1919). From 1919 to 1922, Gesell was professor of physiology at the University of California. He came to the University of Michigan in 1923, where he was appointed the first chairman of the department of physiology. During his tenure, Gesell oversaw the department's move into the newly constructed East Medical Building and recruited new instructors. Gesell remained at the U-M until his death in 1954.
The collection documents both Gesell's professional career and interests as well as the development of the department of physiology under his leadership. The colection consists of Correspondence, medical school faculty minutes, annual reports of the department, lectures, speeches, and material on the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection, 1930; also photograph. The collection is arranged into the following series: Biographical; Correspondence; University of Michigan; and Other Files.
Subjects:
Child welfare--United States.; Gesell, Robert, 1886-1954.; Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Physiology.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physiology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; White House Conference on Child Health and Protection (1930: Washington, D.C.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Gesell, Robert, 1886-1954.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical
  - Biographical directories data sheets (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Undated and 1921-1943, 56 folders (Box 1)
  - 1944-1956, 21 folders (Box 2)
- University of Michigan
  - Medical School
    - Faculty Minutes, 1923-1944, 16 folders (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Material Relating to Faculty Meetings (Box 2)
    - Correspondence with Medical School Dean, undated and 1923-1945, 13 folders (Box 2)
  - Department of Physiology, 1936-1941
    - Annual Reports, 1936-1942 (Box 2)
    - Departmental finances, 1924-1943, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Other University Affairs
    - Correspondence with the Graduate School Dean, 1924-1945, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence with the President's Office, 1923-1945, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence with U-M Secretary Shirley W. Smith, 1923-1945, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence concerning Summer Sessions, 1923-1943, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Committee for Recommending Promotions, 1938-1942 (Box 3)
    - Committee on Honorary Degrees, 1936-1943 (Box 3)
    - University Office of Educational Investigation, 1940-1941, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Other files
  - Rockefeller Foundation Project, 1938-1942 (Box 3)
  - White House Conference on Child Health and Protection, 1929-1930, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Speeches and articles, 9 folders (Box 3)
  - Henry Russel Lecture,1953 (Box 3)
  - Drafts of "Some Biological Aspects of Medicine" (Box 3)
  - Drafts of "Same Biological Aspects of Aging" (Box 3)
  - Photograph (portrait of RG) (Box 3)